<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of compelling men to the Holy Sacrament of the Lord's Supper considered and authority vindicated in it, by the rules of the Gospel, from the common and popular objections against it.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C898</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21713</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12121865</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12121865</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54451</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35606)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54451)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 591:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of compelling men to the Holy Sacrament of the Lord's Supper considered and authority vindicated in it, by the rules of the Gospel, from the common and popular objections against it.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 52, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Abel Swalle ..., and Fincham Gardiner ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54451:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54451:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF <hi>Compelling Men</hi> TO THE Holy Sacrament OF THE LORD'S SUPPER, CONSIDERED.</p>
            <p>And AUTHORITY Vindicated in it, by the Rules of the Goſpel, from the common and Popular Objections againſt it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 14.23.</hi>
               </bibl> Go and compel them to come in, that my houſe may be filled.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Abel Swalle</hi> at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn,</hi> at the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, and <hi>Fincham Gardiner,</hi> at the <hi>White-horſe</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:54451:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54451:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Beſeech thee believe, that it is not to irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate or incenſe Authority againſt any deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Men, that this Caſe is ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly conſidered. I hope the Clergy of this City have given ſuch Inſtances of their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Candor to thoſe that differ from them, that they ſhall not now be repreſented as men of Sanguinary Diſpoſitions, and Movers of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            <p>And if after all their labour and pains to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and perſwade men, and give them ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in all their great doubts, upon which they ſeparate from the Communion of the Church, they muſt yet be reproached as Cruel, and Perſecutors of their Brethren; it is but another taſte of that Civility that they meet with from this Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>I know of no other deſign in theſe Papers, (and I am ſure I have moſt reaſon to know) but to remove an Exception, that ſome have cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly taken againſt coming to the Sacrament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are forced to do ſo; and to diſcharge ſome
<pb facs="tcp:54451:3"/>part of that duty that we owe to our Superiours, with which the Author thinks it ſcarce conſiſtent, to hear men belch and rayl againſt the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the preſent proceedings of it, without opening our mouths in their defence; eſpecially when what they do, is ſo very fairly capable of it.</p>
            <p>This I think an inſtance of that duty we owe to thoſe above us; out of which could we be fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with hard words and ill Names, we ſhould have deſerted it long ſince for this is not the firſt time (I wiſh it might be the laſt) that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and endeavours of ſervice to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have been made our Crime, and miniſtred to the ill uſage we have met with from Some men.</p>
            <p>I hope, all the Exceptions againſt this great Service in our Religion, will in time be ſingly conſidered, and ſatisfyed; and this is therefore crowded into the number of them; and if it ſeem new or ſtrange, thoſe croſs and wayward tempers of men are only to be charged, which have made this a new and ſtrange Exception.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54451:3"/>
            <head>THE CASE OF <hi>Compelling Men</hi> TO the HOLY SACRAMENT.</head>
            <p>I Can ſcarce ever read our Saviours famous Parable of the Noble-man's making a great Feaſt, ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out ſervants to invite gueſts, the unſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of their invitation, and the ſilly unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy excuſes framed againſt it, till at laſt the Lord was conſtrained to arm other Servants with power, and to <hi>compel them to come in,</hi> but my mind is ſtill run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a Parallel between theſe things, and our own preſent circumſtances, with reſpect to the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord's Supper, as well as ſome other things.</p>
            <p>God Almighty hath been in this, as gracious to us, as ever he was to his own people the <hi>Jews.</hi> He hath provided all things neceſſary to our Salvation; and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, hath furniſhed a Table with the precious Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols of his own Son's Body and Blood; <hi>That bread that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54451:4"/>came down from Heaven, and is meat indeed;</hi> and that wine that would chear our hearts, and fill them with a joy that the world is a ſtranger to; the luſhious and ſweet Feaſt in which we antedate Heaven, and make ſeiſure of, and receive pledges for the happineſs of it.</p>
            <p>But alas, our folly and madneſs is equal to theirs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: we turn our backs upon theſe Heavenly proviſions, and frame Apologies and Excuſes againſt them. We let every ſilly occaſion ſuperſede our regard to them, and ſeek for Arguments to furniſh us with Reaſons of keeping from them.</p>
            <p>God keeps up a race of his ſervants the Prophets, whoſe ſtanding employment and office it is, to ſtrive with us, and to perſwade us to accept of that mighty Salvation that is provided for us, and to partake of this ſervice which is ſo greatly conducive to all the purpoſes of it; and I think it may modeſtly be ſaid, they are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to their charge.</p>
            <p>Yet alas, how few will hear their report, ſo as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the end of it? what a few can they perſwade to become gueſts to their Lord? and how long will it be e're his Table be ſo full, that they may not ſay as the ſervant in the Parable did, <hi>It is done, Lord, as thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandedſt us, and yet there is room?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall we ſay to this neglect of men! ſhall we ſtand bewayling, and inveighing againſt the folly and madneſs of it? we have done that long enough, even till our throats are dry; and yet to very little purpoſe, God knows. What have we now left, but to get us to our great Maſter, and tell the ſad ſtory of mens obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy to him? how juſtly might we beg him to take the matter into his own hand; to ſend out other ſervants more noble than we, and arm them with power to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel men to come in?</hi> juſt as that Maſter in the Parable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54451:4"/>did in the like caſe, command his <hi>ſervant to go out into the high ways and hedges, and compel them to come in, that my houſe may be filled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo it is, the wiſdom of Authority hath prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, and ſaved us the labour of making this requeſt; it hath thought fit to take the matter into it's own hand, in a great meaſure, and to revive the Laws that the Piety and Wiſdom of our Fore-fathers have thought fit to make, to ingage men to a due care and obſervance of the Services of Religion: and I would men would conſider, whether this can be thought leſs than neceſſary, and whether they have not been fairly proceeded with.</p>
            <p>Hitherto all fair means have been uſed; nothing but love and kindneſs, and all poſſible condeſcenſion. Men have been indulged in their petulancy, and time allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their prejudices and prepoſſeſſions to wear off in. The Rod of the Law hath been only held over them, but not ſuffered to fall on them. Authority hath been pleaſed to wait, till the common objection of one great Party among us, is taken wholly away.</p>
            <p>The great Plea againſt Conformity, for twenty years paſt, hath been the <hi>obligation of the Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> which ſome of the Leaders of that great Party had taken; and it hath been publickly declared, that were not the renouncing of that required, they would conform.</p>
            <p>The time that this was required for, is now expired, and they are at liberty from that which they counted grievous to them: but now, inſtead of the promiſed Conformity, there are new Arguments ſtarted againſt it, and all the old ones furbiſhed afreſh; the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Church more ſturdy and obſtinate (if it be poſſible) than before, and all the pretences of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in this matter, ſhewed plainly to be meer trick and artifice.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:54451:5"/>
            <p>This therefore hath forced Authority to take other meaſures, and to try what the ſtricter hand of Law will do with them, upon whom indulgence and kindneſs have been ſo ineffectual; and whether they may not tye men to that duty, to which they cannot perſwade them.</p>
            <p>They have ſadly ſeen how little lenity and kindneſs can oblige, and how far favour is from endearing ſome men; yea, that it hath unhappily rendred them worſe, more bold, and more extravagant in their Separation; made them only more keen and eager againſt the Church, and given them the fairer opportunity to wreak their malice upon her; which they had ſo dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently improved, that they had brought her near to a <hi>Criſis</hi> indeed, and were in a fair way of effecting their purpoſe, when as groſs Hereticks as ever were, yea, when black Atheiſts were called the only <hi>True Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Jargon</hi> of different and contrary Sects Marſhall'd in one Body, as well as under one Name, to fight againſt her.</p>
            <p>Yea, they have ſeen and felt ſomething more than this, that tender Conſciences have too commonly hard hands, and that the pulling down the Church, hath been but a Prologue and ſtep to diſſolving the State. Some men have begun with the Supremacy and faults of <hi>Aaron,</hi> only that they might the more ſucceſsfully caſt down the Government of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and fright men from the Communion of the Church, the more eaſily to muſter them againſt the King: and therefore made it neceſſary for the Government to provide againſt the one, if they intended to ſecure and preſerve the other.</p>
            <p>They have thought it high time therefore now to change their meaſures; and to exerciſe Power, when Mildneſs and Clemency would not prevail.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:54451:5"/>
            <p>And this is one thing that hath raiſed the clamour, and enraged men to inveigh againſt Proceedings ſo lowdly at preſent: <hi>What, muſt men be driven like beaſts? muſt they be compelled to that Service which ought to be free and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary? is this Chriſtian dealing? or the way to make Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts? can this bring men to Church, or engage them to offer a reaſonable Service to God there? it may poſſibly make Hypocrites, and cauſe time-ſervers to come in; but ſure the Faith of men cannot be forced, nor they ever brought in love with Religion and the Service of it, by ſuch means.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, and ſuch as theſe are the common clamours of men againſt theſe Proceedings of Authority; and the truth is, (by the way) it lets us ſee how ſtrangely frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard and peeviſh ſome men are. But a little while ago, the common cry and objection was, want of Diſcipline among us; but now, that we are too ſtrict in it. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore we were derided and cenſured for ſlackneſs and remiſneſs, for taking too little care of Religion; but now we are blamed for taking too much. So very contrary pretences can ſome men make uſe of againſt the Church and Government, and wreſt every thing that they do, or do not, into an Argument againſt them.</p>
            <p>I am not willing to reflect farther upon this petulan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; my Province at preſent is to ſhew the injuſtice and unreaſonableneſs of it, and to vindicate this proceeding of our Governours from thoſe aſperſions and reproaches that are caſt upon them. And I ſhall lay the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Apology upon that paſſage of our Saviour, in the Parable I have been alluding to; <hi>Go and compel them to come in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is probable, it will be ſaid, that this is only a by-expreſſion, and far enough from the purport and deſign of this Parable; and therefore to argue from it, is againſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54451:6"/>that common rule that Divines have agreed upon, that Parables are not to be argued from, but only in the main thing intended by them.</p>
            <p>To this it will be eaſie to anſwer, that though it be indeed ſo as is urged, yet our collection relies upon a certain reaſon, and that is the Decorum and Propriety of ſpeaking that our Saviour obſerved in all his Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and how far he was from expreſſing any thing in unjuſtifiable or unbecoming Phraſes, though it were a thing purely incidental, and were never ſo much colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral, or beſide the great matter that he intended to ſay.</p>
            <p>To be ſure, he would never have aſcribed ſuch a thing as this to God Almighty, under the perſon of this great man, though never ſo much by the by, had it been ſo unbecoming, and contrary to his diſpenſations with men; nor ever have mentioned his commanding his ſervants to <hi>compel men to come in</hi> to Religion, and the Miniſtries of it, had it been unlawful, and contrary to the temper of the Goſpel (as is pretended) to uſe any force at all, either to reſtrain men from evil, or tye them to that which is good. We may reſt aſſured, that no ſuch expreſſion had ever fallen from him, had he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that every man ſhould be purely at his own liberty in Religion, to do, or not to do what himſelf pleaſed.</p>
            <p>So that I think this expreſſion will favour our purpoſe, and be a good foundation to ſuperſtruct an Argument upon. In the proſecution of which, I ſhall do theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Propoſe ſome general and more abſtracted Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, for the juſtifying the preſent proceedings in this caſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And ſecondly, inquire immediately into the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Cauſe, and examine it by the rules and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Goſpel.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54451:6"/>
            <p n="1">1. The general Conſiderations I intend, are theſe that follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That whatever is done of this nature, is done by our lawful Governours.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is done by thoſe whoſe Authority reacheth to theſe things, and who are accountable to God for them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is done in a matter which is in it ſelf lawful, and plainly juſtified by the Laws of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is in a matter which is greatly gainful and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to thoſe that are commanded.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is occaſioned only by our ſelves, and our own unreaſonable neglect of our duty.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is nothing elſe, but what thoſe very men that complain, have done in the like, or leſſer caſes.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is no harm or injury to theſe men, upon their own common Principles.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whatever is done of this nature, is done by our lawful Governours. I ſhall not need I hope to have any controverſie with men about this, nor will any (I believe) dare to diſpute the truth of it: though we poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly may have enough to queſtion the Government of the Church, yet certainly that of the Kingdom is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable with any, but men of deſperate and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Principles, and impatient of any Government but that which themſelves manage.</p>
            <p>Now this alone is one good ſtep towards vindicating what is now done, and one good argument for mens Obedience and Submiſſion unto it. For it is ſcarce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming men to diſpute and queſtion the actions of their lawful Governours in any thing; but to revile and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach them is lawful in none.</p>
            <p>Subjection is tyed immediately upon the Conſciences of men, and obedience in all things (not eſſentially evil)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54451:7"/>is a duty of Religion. By the ſame right that a Parent commands his Child, and a Maſter his Servant, by the ſame doth the King govern us; and we have no more right to quarrel the commands of the one, than Children and Servants have to repine and murmur at the precepts of the other; which they never have, but when either Parents or Maſters exerciſe an authority that doth no way belong to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Which in our caſe is not done: for Secondly, it is done by thoſe whoſe power reacheth to theſe things, and who ſtand accountable to God for them.</p>
            <p>The power of Kings in Spiritual Matters, was never queſtioned (that I know of) in the Chriſtian Church, till Pride and Ambition began to corrupt it's Faith, and poiſon it's Doctrine, and till <hi>Rome</hi> began to aim at a Spiritual Empire, as well as it had had a Temporal one.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of diſcarding Kings and Emperours from any intermedling in Religion, was firſt hammered in the Conclave, and thence our Claſſical Divines have fetched it; and I wiſh it were the only inſtance, in which they ſymbolize with thoſe, that they ſo lowdly declaim againſt.</p>
            <p>I am ſure the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſuperviſed, and when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion was, reformed matters of Religion and the Church; and the better that they were, the more they intereſted themſelves, and employed their care about them; and embalmed their Names more by that, than all their Arms and glorious Atchievements. And when the Apoſtle commands Chriſtians to <hi>pray for Kings, that they might live honeſt and godly</hi> (i. e. religious) <hi>lives un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them,</hi> he certainly thought their influence might be greatly helpful thereunto.</p>
            <p>And the truth is, I do not well ſee how Kings and Governours can blaſt their honour more, and more blacken their own name, than by looking only to their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54451:7"/>own grandour and honour, without any concern for his, whoſe Vice-gerents they are, by living themſelves in glorious and <hi>Ceiled Houſes,</hi> but letting <hi>that of God</hi> lye neglected and waſt, as the expreſſions in the Prophet are.</p>
            <p>Certainly, when the great and final Audit comes, and when the Kings and Princes of the world come to ſtand before him <hi>by whom they Reigned,</hi> who is <hi>King of Kings; and Lord of Lords;</hi> one great Inquiry will be, how faithful they have been to him their great Maſter, and how much or how little they have conſulted his honour and intereſt in the world: and thoſe doubtleſs will give their accounts with moſt joy to themſelves, and moſt acceptation to him, that have been tender of his Church, and conſulted the benefit of his Religion; that have been <hi>nurſing Fathers</hi> to the one, and tender of the other, and uſed their power to keep men in their duty to him and his Laws, as well as to their own.</p>
            <p>And the Governours in the Church, and thoſe that are <hi>over us in the Lord,</hi> they <hi>watch for our Souls</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Paul) and muſt give account</hi> for them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 16.17.</p>
            <p>So that we muſt not think that our Governours ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the bounds and limits of their own power, when they make Laws about Religion, and tye us to obſerve the ſervices of it; or that they do theſe things arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily only, and to exerciſe their power over us; no, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe are true; their power reacheth to theſe things, and they are bound by their great Lord to take all the care they can of them: and therefore we muſt excuſe them; they do but their own duty to God which they compel us to do ours.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And that this is really our duty, and tyed upon us by the Laws of the Goſpel, is the third Conſideration; and will adde another reaſon to vindicate them in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling us to it.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:54451:8"/>
            <p>If this thing were contrary to the Goſpel, then we might juſtly complain of their rigor and ſeverity; or were it left wholly indifferent, then we might raiſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, and pretend invaſion of our Chriſtian liberty by theſe Laws, as tragically as we do in the like caſes.</p>
            <p>But when it is a thing plainly and expreſly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by our Saviour, and tyed upon us as a conſtant and ſtanding ſervice of Religion, to be obſerved and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by all Chriſtians until his ſecond coming again, (as it is moſt plain it is, if we will either conſider his own words, or St. <hi>Pauls</hi> after him) then certainly there cannot be the leaſt room for an objection in this matter.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that ſay the leaſt of the power of Kings and Temporal Governours, do ſay they are obliged to ſee that the precepts of God be obſerved and kept by men, and that they are to inforce the Laws of Religion by their own; and when it is for their purpoſe, will boldly call for this exerciſe of their power; ſummon the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Sword and Arms, when their own Spiritual ones are too weak; and be ready to <hi>anathematize and curſe</hi> thoſe powers, that in this <hi>come not to help the Lord againſt the mighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It it be their own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Religion, why then it is <hi>the Scepter of Chriſt,</hi> whom all Kings are bound to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; and if it be any thing that they lack to have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, why then it is <hi>the Lords cauſe;</hi> and the ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, is no leſs than <hi>fighting the Lords battel,</hi> for which the higheſt Praiſes and Panegyricks are too little.</p>
            <p>And therefore methinks men of this temper, and who are yet known to have acted ſtill upon this principle, ſhould for ſhame ceaſe to complain &amp; cry out againſt the Government, for uſing their power in that, which they themſelves allow the exerciſe of it lawful in; and not condemn it, when it compels men to nothing, but what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54451:8"/>the Laws of Chriſt have made their neceſſary du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Yea and fourthly, which is as really their intereſt and advantage, as it is their duty; for ſo it is in this as well as in all other precepts of the Goſpel; they are real inſtruments of our happineſs, as well as inſtances of our obedience.</p>
            <p>I cannot now ſtand to enumerate all the benefits and advantages of receiving the Holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper; and I need to do it the leſs, becauſe the Church hath done it for me. I will only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the words in her Catechiſme, which are ſufficient at this time: <hi>The ſtrengthning and refreſhing out Souls by the Body and Blood of Chriſt, as our Bodies are by the Bread and Wine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And certainly, if any thing can be an Apologie for the preſent exerciſe of power in our Governours, in conſtraining men to an obſervance of this ſervice, this may; that it is a matter of pure kindneſs, and nothing but their own gain, that they are compelled unto: they are ſeverely dealt with indeed in this, and a mighty wrong ſure is done them, when they are compelled to be made happy and good!</p>
            <p>All the world hath ever granted it lawful and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, nay, prudent and wiſe, to direct and govern thoſe who are not able to govern and chooſe for themſelves: Parents reſtrain the ignorance of Children, and think it no crime to whip them to that duty and exerciſe which they know to be good for them: and Guardians do the ſame thing too for their Minors; what they are aſſured is for their benefit, they compel them unto, though it be never ſo irkſome to them, and ſpare not for their much crying: juſt as Chirurgions and Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians conſult the good, and not the eaſe and palate of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54451:9"/>their patients; and forbear not the cauſtick or the ſawe, or the bitteteſt potion, though perhaps the Patient muſt be bound in one caſe, and be even conſtrained in the other.</p>
            <p>It is juſt the ſame caſe here; only ſo much the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter benefit, by how much the ſpirit and it's Salvation is better than the body; and if there be any to complain of, eertainly 'tis only our own ſelves.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And that's the fifth thing I propoſed to conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for all this is occaſioned only by our own default: and it is not very eaſie to ſay, whether men be more condemnable for their wilful falling into ſuch an evil, or their complaining that means are uſed for their recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. It is imprudent to hurt and miſchief themſelves, but it is much more to quarrel with the charity of thoſe that would help them.</p>
            <p>Would men be pleaſed to live ſo like Subjects, as not to occaſion any fear or jealouſie to the Government, and would they pleaſe to keep themſelves in the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church, and a regular obſervance of the Services and Miniſtries of Religion; they would never hear of any trouble, nor need to complain of any force or violence againſt them.</p>
            <p>But if they will be heaving at Government, and will be factious, and innovate in Religion, the more eaſily and ſucceſsfully to accompliſh their other evil deſigns; they muſt thank themſelves, if the edge of the Law be turned on them; and if they be a little ſtricter held to their duty, they muſt blame only their own wilful neglect and diſregard of it. In this caſe they have none to complain againſt but themſelves: for Authority, if it have any regard to it ſelf, or any concern for them, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do leſs than it doth, without betraying it's own truſt, and caſting off all concern for thoſe that God hath given it the charge and care of.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:54451:9"/>
            <p n="6">6. But ſixthly, there is another conſideration to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mens complaints and murmurings againſt this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure unjuſt; and that is, that they themſelves have done the ſame thing, or worſe, in the like or leſſer caſes.</p>
            <p>Time was, when any one that did not ſwear as faſt as they would have them, and count their Covenant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Sacred ſhould not only be Excommunicated, but Out-law'd, and put immediately from under the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and protection of Law.</p>
            <p>And we have lately ſeen how forward theſe very perſons that now complain, have been to put Teſts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all others; and to injoyn all in any Office or Place of truſt, to receive the Sacrament, upon forfeiture of the Place, and a great ſum beſides.</p>
            <p>And I wiſh I could not ſay, to the ſhame of ſome, and their unanſwerable reproach, how readily they could receive it, when their profit and intereſt invited them, though they complain and grumble, when it is made their duty; and labour to ſcare others from it under the notion of Superſtition and Idolatry.</p>
            <p>Intereſt (we may ſee) will eaſily anſwer all Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and be able to do more, than all the beſt arguments in the world beſides: and were but the Sacrament now a Band and Cement of Union among themſelves a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federating the more cloſely to carry on their own pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, or any way ſubſervient to their deſign, we ſhould hear of no complaints, nor invectives againſt any, but thoſe that refuſed ſo holy and ſaying an Ordinance.</p>
            <p>This is the plain truth of the thing; and if men be offended at it, we cannot help it, nor ought much to be concerned; and therefore it is a ſtark ſhame for thoſe to complain againſt the preſent proceedings of Authority, who have gone before them in the ſame, and much worſe. It is a hard thing for us to be <hi>judged</hi> by them, who do themſelves the very <hi>ſame thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:54451:10"/>
            <p n="7">7. And laſtly, the complaining will be the more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, when it is no injury at all to them, upon their own principles; nor doing any thing to them, which they do not wilfully to themſelves.</p>
            <p>It is too evident what little reſpect theſe men bear to the Church, and how little they value the Communion of it: they ſeparate themſelves from it, and avow a downright Schiſm againſt it: and therefore what inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (I pray) can Excommunication be to ſuch men? It is they that anticipate Excommunication, thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of the Church, and defie it, and perſiſt in plain contempt of it; and what Authority doth, is little elſe than barely declaring what they have done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>And I am verily perſwaded, were it not for ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of it, and ſome prejudice that might redound from it to their Temporal concern, they would as little regard it, as they do the Church; deride it as <hi>brutum fulmen,</hi> and no more dread it, than men do fire painted upon a wall.</p>
            <p>We that can hear men ridiculing the notion of a Church, and laughing at all the diſcourſes about Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with it, do very well know how little they va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, or think themſelves hurt, by being Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and turned out of that, which they never deſire to be of: they that can ſo lowdly confront all Antiquity, and in ſpight of all the Fathers of the Church, and Maxims of the Apoſtles too, teach <hi>Salvation to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable as well out of the Church as in it,</hi> certainly can never think themſelves injured by being caſt out of it; and all their Tragical complaints of Perſecution in this, are but artifice and hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>Men may be driven, indeed, to that which they do not love; but they are but compelled by that, which they do not much dread or fear.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:54451:10"/>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing propoſed, is to inquire into the nature and meaſures of that compulſion, that the Laws and Precedents of the Goſpel do warrant in this caſe; and then to try, whether the preſent proceedings of Authority againſt men, may not be juſtified upon them.</p>
            <p>This is a thing the more needful to be ſtated with heed and caution, becauſe the great Clamour is upon it. And two things with great confidence are urged by men, upon which they take upon them to cenſure the preſent proceedings of Authority, as wholly contrary to the Doctrine and ſpirit of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is not conſonant to the Goſpel to uſe any force at all to men in matters of Religion; and that nothing but Papal uſurpation and cruelty hath introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the practice of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That however, if there be any footſteps of force and rigour then, or that the Goſpel mention any ſuch thing, yet that rigour was purely Spiritual. Church-cenſures were her only Arms, and Excommunication the only puniſhment that ſhe did inflict; but the Body and Eſtate, and the external concerns of men were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched.</p>
            <p>But (ſo ſay they) theſe are not now: did Authority content it ſelf only to go thus far, we ſhould bear it, and ſhould have nothing to object againſt it; but now mens civil intereſts are touched, mens perſons or purſes may pay for it. There is a Writ <hi>de Capie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>do Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicato,</hi> and there are ſharp Laws for puniſhing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy of thoſe, that obſtinately refuſe ſubmiſſion and compliance.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the popular, and (in ſome mens appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion) very plauſible exceptions againſt theſe things. It will the more concern me therefore, clearly to ſtate this matter. And if I can make theſe two things clear
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54451:11"/>in oppoſition to what is objected. I ſhall do enough in this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Doctrine of the Goſpel doth warrant the Exerciſe of force and rigour, in matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where men will not be governed, and kept within due bounds, by the precepts and rules of it, and a conſcience of their duty: and the Hiſtory of it, and the Primitive times, do furniſh us with examples and prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents enough of that rigour; and therefore that this was not introduced by Popiſh uſurpation, as is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That theſe puniſhments were not purely Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, but extended and reached to the perſons, and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal intereſts of men; both which ſuffered as much, or more than they do now.</p>
            <p>If I can clear the truth and certainty of theſe two things, I ſhall fully ſatisfie the Objections, and lay a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſoundation to juſtifie the preſent proceedings of Authority upon.</p>
            <p>To this therefore I now addreſs my ſelf, with all the plainneſs and clearneſs that I can: beſeeching any, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that are under any diſſatisfaction in theſe things, to conſider honeſtly and impartially what I am going to ſay.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And firſt, that the Doctrine of the Goſpel doth warrant the exerciſe of force and rigour in matters of Religion, where the Conſcience of duty will not keep men in order And that we are furniſhed with precedents and examples of this, I think is very clear, to all that have either conſidered the conſtitution of the Chriſtian Church, or taken notice of thoſe Remarks of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of it, which they meet with in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If it would be ſufficient conviction to ſome men, to argue this from principles of true reaſon, or from
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54451:11"/>conſequences that fairly and naturally offer themſelves from premiſſes that are certain and uncontroverted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all men, it might be enough to put the matter upon that iſſue.</p>
            <p>And then I would only conſider what is granted on all hands, <hi>viz</hi> That Chriſt hath founded himſelf a Church in the world; not contenting himſelf only to have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons come to the knowledge of the truth as it is in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; to become Proſelytes to the Chriſtian Religion, and to be won over to the Faith of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>But that he hath formed all theſe perſons into a Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, caſt them into one common Body, of which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is the Head; made his Church a Spiritual Politie, and united all Chriſtians as Members of it, by proper and ſtrong bands and ligatures; and made the greateſt part of their duty to conſiſt, not ſo much in acting in a ſingle and independent capacity; as in the diſcharge of thoſe Offices that become them as members conſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and united together in one common body.</p>
            <p>For ſo we know the greateſt part of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion conſiſts in the publick worſhip of God and Chriſt, with one heart and one conſent; the glorifying God with one mouth, and in meekneſs and love; in condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention and charity one to another, and a ſtrict union and peace among themſelves.</p>
            <p>I need not ſtand arguing the truth of this; it is plain of it ſelf in the New Teſtament, and confeſſed by all Sides and Parties of men at this day: though I muſt needs ſay, the ſerious belief and conſideration of it, would alone umpire and iſſue moſt of the diſputes that are among us, about Conformity, and Schiſm, and Separation at the preſent.</p>
            <p>But I am ſure it is a ſufficient foundation for what I am undertaking to prove; and there are theſe two things that do moſt naturally and neceſſarily follow from it.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:54451:12"/>
            <p n="1">1. That therefore Chriſt hath veſted this Church of his, with all that authority and power, that is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary for the conſervation of it ſelf as a Body and a Society, <hi>i. e.</hi> for the preſervation of order and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for their keeping all its members in a due regard to the Laws and Conſtitutions of it.</p>
            <p>And this is ſo certain, as it is that Chriſt Jeſus is good and wiſe, and one that would never defeat his own deſigns, nor command order and unity to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in his Church, without induing it with that power which was abſolutely neceſſary to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>It is ſo reflective upon the wiſdom of a man, to caſt men into ſociety, and unite them under any Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without contriving ſome effectual means for the preſervation and maintenance of order among them as ſuch, that we can't think it competent to the Son of God, without the higheſt blaſphemy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That therefore he hath veſted his Church, and the Governours of it, with a power of inſlicting puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and uſing rigour againſt its members, where the ſenſe and conſcience of their duty would not keep them in order.</p>
            <p>There can be no doubt of this, nor any reaſon to queſtion the certainty of it; for this power is alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely neceſſary to the preſervation of the Church: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we do ſuppoſe that all the members of it are, and ever will be ſo conſcientious and good, us to be kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their compaſs, by a ſenſe of their duty, and a reſpect to the great arguments that the Goſpel uſeth to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And I readily confeſs, that were all Chriſtians ſuch as they ſhould be, and as the Laws of the Goſpel require them to be, this power that I am contending for, might be thought unneceſſary for the Church, and thereupon be argued not to be granted to it.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:54451:12"/>
            <p>But alas, we ſee too clearly, that it is quite otherwiſe; and he that better knew what was in man than we, hath plainly told us, that it always was, and will be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; and that he doth in repreſenting it as a mixed multitude, as a parcel of ground wherein was ſtony, and barren, and thorny uncultivated land, as well as good, and well prepared; as a field wherein there were tares and weeds, as well as wheat and good grain; as a net caſt into the ſes, which brought up of every kind, and wherein were refuſe and vile, as well as good and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome fiſh: all which you may ſee illuſtrated clearly, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>And we have clear Specimens of this truth in his own firſt collection of Diſciples and followers; of the one of which we read of a great many at one time going off, and forſaling him; and of a <hi>Judas</hi> and a Devil even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſmall company of his twelve Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>And alſo in the firſt foundations of a Church that his Apoſtles laid after him, in one of which you read of an <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> in another of a <hi>Demas;</hi> in one, of an Incoſtuous perſon, and Schiſmaticks, and in another, of thoſe that walked <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> diſorderly, breaking their ranks, forſaking their proper ſtation, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering upon anothers Office and Place; and St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of a great many of Apoſtates that went out from them, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19.</p>
            <p>And the Apoſtles frequently warn us of falſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Apoſtates, of Seducers and Deceivers, and of men of the very worſt Characters, that ſhould yet have a form of godlineſs, and put on the name and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zor of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>And the truth is, as long as men are men, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in this imperfect ſtate, we cannot expect it ſhould be otherwiſe. There will be Hypocrites in the Church, and men that make Religion a deſign, and receive not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54451:13"/>the truth in love, but have by-ends and purpoſes of their own to ſerve, and when it ſerves theſe, will be ready to deſtroy, and cauſe Factions in the Church, and betray Religion, as well as at other times to profeſs great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to it: and for any thing I can ſee or learn from the Hiſtories of the Church; it hath been as much peſter'd and troubled by unruly diſorderly members, as almoſt any other Collection or Society of men whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Now to theſe it is plain, ſuch a power as this is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary; and it is not poſſible to keep them in order without it. Men that act not by Conſcience, and a ſenſe of duty, and whom the arguments of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and the ſenſe of immortality will not hold, nothing but the rod and external correction can take hold of.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Church muſt either have power to puniſh them, and inflict ſuch ſeverities upon them as they regard, and can be reſtrained by; or elſe it muſt be left defenceleſs and unregarded, expoſed to all their malice, and without any remedy againſt thoſe miſchiefs that Faction and unrulineſs always produce: <hi>i. e.</hi> it may at any time be in the power of her wicked members to work her ruine and diſorder, and ſhe be wholly deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of any remedy to help her ſelf againſt them.</p>
            <p>Which if any man can believe to be according to the mind and conſtitution of Chriſt, he muſt at the ſame time believe, that Chriſt founded his Church in vain, or out of the greateſt malice to her, in expoſing her cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to the aſſaults and injuries of her wicked and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten members, without any ordinary means of defence againſt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or ſecondly, if it would be ſufficient to argue from thoſe precepts and charges that are in the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical writings, yea in the Goſpel it ſelf given to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the Church in general, <hi>of feeding the flock, of keeping out thoſe ravenous and greedy wolves that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54451:13"/>would ſtrive to break in upon it, of watching over it, of ſilencing gain-ſayers, of ſtopping the mouth of thoſe that taught any other Doctrine, of convincing gain-ſayers, of ſharply rebuking the diſorderly and unruly, &amp;c.</hi> many of which are written in almoſt all the Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>I ſay, if we might argue from them, we might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not only the lawfulneſs, but ſometimes the expedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and neceſſity of this power: for otherwiſe the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church were commanded to do that, which were impoſſible to be done, and forbid the exerciſe of that power which was abſolutely neceſſary to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that, which they had an expreſs charge to ſee to the doing of; which were ſomething worſe, and more tyrannical in their Maſter, than <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> exacting brick of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of old, without allowing them ſtraw to burn them with.</p>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations, and theſe Arguments from them, might be enough to iſſue this queſtion, and to convince all men, that act by Reaſon, and upon the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of it. But to others, plain matter of fact will be more affecting; and thoſe that call upon us ſo loudly, to produce any example of this under the Goſpel, will be more ſatisfied by ſhewing them plain precedents of that, which we are pleading for, or expreſs places of Scripture to warrant the ſame.</p>
            <p>And firſt, for a place of Scripture to warrant this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I think that of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, where he directs us, as the laſt remedy againſt a Brother that injures us, to tell the Fact to the Church. Which though I confeſs it may intend only his higher conviction and ſhame, and a more probable way of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing him fairly to repair the wrong; yet I doubt not but it means more, and is in effect an appealing to a higher Tribunal, whoſe commands ſhould he ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard, as to cauſe them to paſs cenſure upon him,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54451:14"/>afterwards he ſhould be reputed a <hi>Heathen</hi> and a <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican,</hi> forfeit all that reſpect and charity that he might otherwiſe expect and claim from us. And this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation I am the more confirmed in, becauſe I find the ſame thing injoyned to an Excommunicated per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9, and 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14.</p>
            <p>And that this was our Saviours meaning, may be ſtrongly concluded from the conſonant directions of his Apoſtles, who injoyn the exerciſe of ſuch a power, in caſes of Scandal and great Offences; as is plain in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> command to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> in the caſe of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous perſon, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.3, 4, 5. <hi>For I verily have judged already concerning him that hath done this thing, in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt when ye are gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, and my ſpirit, with the power of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> (i. e. that power which he hath given me) <hi>to deliver ſuch a one unto Satan for the deſtruction of the fleſh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And this power he would have exerciſed alſo, not only againſt that ſingle perſon, but equally againſt any other that is an incorrigible Fornicator, or Covetous, or an Idolater, or a Rayler, or a Drunkard, or an Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11.</p>
            <p>And much what the ſame to this, he recommends to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> to be done to thoſe that <hi>walk diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly,</hi> as was juſt now hinted, and did not obey the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of the Apoſtle to them, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6.11.14.</p>
            <p>And conſonant directions he gives to <hi>Titus, Cap.</hi> 1.11. and particularly concerning a Heretick, <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.10. <hi>A man that is an Heretick after the firſt and ſecond admonition re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> i. e. Excommunicate.</p>
            <p>And that the Apoſtles did themſelves act according to this rule when occaſion was, you have clear inſtances, in St. <hi>Peters</hi> cenſure upon <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira, Acts</hi> 5.5.10. which example became of moſt excellent effect,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54451:14"/>ſaith St. <hi>Luke,</hi> to reſtrain all men from any the like ſins, <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>Great fear came upon all the Church, and upon as many as heard theſe things;</hi> who plainly perceived that the Apoſtles had a power to correct and puniſh them, if they did amiſs.</p>
            <p>The like you read done by St. <hi>Paul</hi> againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous <hi>Corinthian,</hi> the caſe but now mentioned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. and alſo againſt <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. <hi>whom I have delivered unto Satan, that they may learn not to blaſpheme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I think few things can be plainlier ſpoken of, than this power is in ſeveral places in his Epiſtles to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians;</hi> particularly in theſe that follow, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>ult. What will ye? ſhall I come unto you with a rod, or in love, and in the ſpirit of meekneſs?</hi> where by the Rod, <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> and others underſtand the power of inflicting death, as upon <hi>Ananias;</hi> blindneſs, as upon <hi>Elymas</hi> the Sorcerer, or other diſeaſes; making the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſame with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. which ſignifie puniſhment, and corporal inflictions; for ſo, ſaith he, God then ſupplied the defect of that which Civil Magiſtrates ought to do againſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate offenders; and which was not done then, becauſe the Government was not become Chriſtian. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6. <hi>Having in a readineſs to revenge all diſobedience:</hi> and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.10. <hi>Therefore I write theſe things being abſent, leſt being preſent, I ſhould uſe ſharpneſs, according to the power which the Lord hath given to me,</hi> i. e. that power of puniſhing obſtinate offenders with diſeaſes, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral puniſhments; as the ſame <hi>Grotius,</hi> and others with him, expound it.</p>
            <p>So that if either plain directions for the exerciſe of ſuch a power, or inſtances of the actual execution of it, will convince men of the lawfulneſs of it, we ſhall not hear it any more queſtioned.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:54451:15"/>
            <p>And it is ſo well known, that the Primitive Church thought theſe ſo good and full warrant for their doing the like, that it was commonly in all ſuch caſes exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then, againſt notorious and ſcandalous offenders; and continued ſince in every age of it, even unto this day. And ſome Councels have expreſly ordered it againſt the wilful neglect and contempt, nay the diſuſe of the Lords Supper in particular: which gives us a plain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and preſident of it, in that very particular caſe of ours, which we are now ſpeaking of.</p>
            <p>This I think is enough upon the firſt thing propoſed, and ſufficient to convince all, that the Goſpel doth not allow every man in Chriſtian Religion to act as he liſt, and to be under no rule but his own pleaſure; but that it requires men to be ſubject to the Conſtitutions of the Church, and hath veſted it with a power to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel men to obſerve the Inſtitutions of Chriſtianity, when the arguments thereof will not perſwade them thereunto.</p>
            <p>But this is the leſſer part of my undertaking; for I believe few, when they conſider better, will deny me this: for all ſides allow it, and all ſorts practiſe according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon their own members. There is not the wildeſt and moſt confuſed Sect among them, that have come to any head, (no not the Quakers) but will exerciſe a power over their own members, and uſe rigor and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, where gentle means will not do. And therefore cannot quarrel with the exerciſe of Excommunication, without condemning themſelves, as well as taxing the plain directions and warrant of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I have obſerved therefore, as an addition to this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and a full Anſwer to the Objection, that theſe penalties were not purely Spiritual, but did reach to the perſons and external intereſts of men, both which did ſuffer as much, or more, than they do now; and if I can
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54451:15"/>make this good, I ſuppoſe the Objection can deſire no more, in order to its full anſwer and ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>To this therefore I ſhall now, addreſs my ſelf; and in order thereto, I ſhall do theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall conſider ſome puniſhments inflicted in the Goſpel, which were not only Spiritual, but did reach the body, yea the very life, and all other external inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall conſider the nature of Excommunication in the time of the Apoſtles, and endeavour to prove that it was always attended with external corporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in thoſe times.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To begin with the firſt: there is mention in the New Teſtament of puniſhments inflicted by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles upon offenders, that were not only Spiritual. Of this there is a moſt remarkable inſtance, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. the full ſtory and all the circumſtances of it are related from <hi>v.</hi> 1. to 12. The ſum of the caſe was this. <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> his wife ſold an Eſtate, and pretended to bring the price of it into the common <hi>Fiſcus,</hi> and Bank, to be imployed for the uſe of the whole body of Chriſtians, as the manner then was; but it ſeems kept back part, for their own private uſe.</p>
            <p>Some men perhaps in this age would be apt to think that it was no ſuch great crime: and certainly it had not, had they dealt ſincerely in the caſe, and not diſſembled and cloaked it with a peremptory lye; without which, ſuch an act of Charity now, would be thought ſo far from deſerving a cenſure, that it would procure men the higheſt character for Religion, and inſert their names into the golden Dypticks of the Church.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding this, St. <hi>Peter</hi> not only cenſures them highly for this, but puniſheth them with death. And that you may be ſure this was not Gods own imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate infliction only, &amp; beſides the intention and thought
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54451:16"/>of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> you may ſee him threatning it immediately to <hi>Sapphira, v.</hi> 9. <hi>The feet of them that carried out thy Husband, ſhall carry thee out alſo;</hi> upon which, ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſhe falls down dead.</p>
            <p>This was a ſtartling inſtance indeed! to let men ſee what a dangerous thing it was to violate the inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſtianity, and to act contrary to the practices of the Church, (for this failure, bating the hypocriſie and lye; was but in ſuch a thing) and accordingly it did greatly affect men, and cauſe <hi>great fear to come upon all the Church,</hi> as you are told, <hi>v.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Another inſtance ſomething like this, you meet with, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30. <hi>For this cauſe many are work and ſickly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, and many ſleep:</hi> i.e. becauſe of your profaning and contemning the Lords Supper, many of you ſuffer puniſhments and weakneſſes in your body, and have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes inflicted upon you, and ſome actually dye.</p>
            <p>This is the more conſiderable, and ought to be the more affecting at preſent, I becauſe it is in the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and for that particular fault, which our preſent Queſtion is about, and for which men pretend it to be contrary to the Goſpel to be puniſhed; and that is in the neglect of the holy Sacrament, which certainly is every way as unchriſtian as the profanation of it; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather worſe to neglect and diſregard wholly an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Chriſtianity, than to fail only in the way of performing it.</p>
            <p>I do not underſtand why it ſhould render this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the leſs convictive, to reply, that we do not read that theſe puniſhments were inflicted by the Apoſtle, but immediately by God himſelf: for howſoever that were, yet</p>
            <p n="1">1. It lets us ſee, that ſuch ſailures did deſerve all theſe puniſhments, by whomſoever they were inflicted; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we dare ſay, that God cauſeleſly and unjuſtly afflicts the Sons of men.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:54451:16"/>
            <p n="2">2. It lets us underſtand, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Apoſtle alſo was privy to the deſign of this providence, acquainted with the reaſons of it; and ſo, in ſome kind of ſenſe, of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel with God in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And thirdly, it is plain he uſeth it as an argument to deter them from ſuch things for the future; which had been very precarious and at randome, unleſs he could aſſure them, that ſuch puniſhments ſhould, as well as they had been, be the effect and conſequences of that ſin: for if theſe things were wholly out of his power and cognizance, and depended ſolely upon the will and pleaſure of God, he could not with any good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and certainty, threaten them with them for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for we can't draw certain concluſions from Gods former dealings, nor conclude, Becauſe God hath done thus, therefore he will do the ſame in the like caſes.</p>
            <p>Theſe two inſtances of puniſhments relate to the body and life of a man plainly. I will only adde to them one, which extends as well to his Eſtate, and intereſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, and that is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <hi>But now I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten unto you, not to keep company, if any man that is called a Brother be a Fornicator, or Covetous, or an Idolater, or a Rayler, or a Drunkard, or an Extortioner, with ſuch a one no not to eat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where it is plain, by not keeping company, and not eating, the Apoſtle means to forbid all familiarity, all intercourſe and dealing with ſuch a man, all buying of, or ſelling to, and all manner of trading with him; ſhun him as a plague, and have no more to do with him, than with an infected perſon and a devil: and how diſmal and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitous the caſe of ſuch a man muſt needs be, and how deſtructive this would be of all his intereſt and concern in the world, you will eaſily ſee.</p>
            <p>I am very confident, that if puniſhments equal to any of theſe that I have named, were inflicted upon the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54451:17"/>contemners of the Sacrament now, there would be ſtrange outcries of cruelty, and tragical complaints of perſecution; and the Governours of the Church would be rayled againſt, as unchriſtian, and men that did not act according to the rules of the Goſpel: and yet you ſee theſe things were done in the pureſt times of the Goſpel, and by thoſe men too, that were immediately acted by a Divine Infallible Spirit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, to theſe I ſhall adde another Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, that will bring the matter home, and cloſe to our preſent caſe; and that is, that Excommunication was not purely a Spiritual puniſhment, but attended with external inflictions, as great and terrible, or much more ſo than it is now.</p>
            <p>That Excommunication was a common and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry puniſhment inflicted upon thoſe unruly Chriſtians, whom Conſcience and a ſenſe of duty could not keep in order. I have proved already, and I ſuppoſe ſhall not have it diſputed or queſtioned by any, that I have now a controverſie with.</p>
            <p>The only queſtion is. Whether this was any more than a ſpiritual puniſhment, and went any further than to cutting men off from the Communion of the Church, and from thoſe hopes of future Salvation that the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it did expect; Whether it were not enough to exclude men from all hopes of Heaven, and conſign them inevitably to Hell and eternal damnation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the weaker terrors of corporal and external mulcts and puniſhments.</p>
            <p>Our Adverſaries contend vehemently, that this was all that was in Excommunication of old, and that no thing was ſuffered after it. That this weapon of the Church was according to the language of St. <hi>Paul, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> only, and in no ſenſe <hi>carnal,</hi> or affecting the fleſh; and that therefore any proſecution of Excommunicate
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54451:17"/>perſons, after that ſentence, any inforcing the terror of it by external puniſhments, is wholly unſcriptural, and contrary to the rule of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>This part of the controverſie therefore I am now go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to undertake, and do not at all doubt but to prove, that this is a very groſs (though I hope not wilful) miſtake, and that Excommunication was attended with as great and terrible external ſufferings then, as it can be now, nay much greater.</p>
            <p>And this I ſhall endeavour to prove,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the phraſe and language in which this pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is expreſſed in Scripture.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the teſtimony of Antiquity, and learned men, in this inſtance.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I begin with the firſt, to conſider the phraſe under which the matter of Excommunication is expreſſed in the New Teſtament: and there are but theſe two places that at preſent I remember, in which this is purpoſely and fully done; and they are 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. in which the expreſſion is exactly the ſame. In both places Excommunication is expreſſed by <hi>delivering unto Satan;</hi> only the end of this is a little variouſly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; in one it is added, <hi>For the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the ſpirit may be ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> In the other it is, <hi>That they may learn not to blaſpheme.</hi> I ſhall conſider theſe apart. 1. What Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is here ſaid to be. 2. What the end and purpoſe of it is. Both will be pertinent to my purpoſe, and be good proof of what I am contending for.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I conſider the phraſe that this cenſure is expreſſed in; and that is, <hi>Delivering up unto Satan; To deliver ſuch a one unto Satan,</hi> and <hi>Whom I have delivered unto Satan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which expreſſion we are to underſtand, not only the cutting off from the Communion of the Church,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54451:18"/>the body of Chriſt, and the ſociety of Men, that he hath Impaled to himſelf, and over which his extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary protection and providence watcheth.</p>
            <p>But it means the putting men from under that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon providence and protection of God, that guards all men; and the not only expoſing them to the incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and power of the Devil, but conſigning them ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitably and infallibly to his malice and fury, to be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and afflicted by him.</p>
            <p>For if it were only the firſt of theſe, then it were only the putting men into that eſtate, which all that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace not the belief of the Goſpel are in, and that which all Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, and Apoſtates inflict upon themſelves; over whom yet the common provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God watcheth, and ſaves from many evils, which through the malice of the Devil, and their own folly, they would certainly fall into. It would be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrent to Chriſtian charity to ſay, that all ſuch perſons and Nations are thus given up to Satan, and that Divine providence neglects, and takes no care of them.</p>
            <p>It means therefore the execrating and devoting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons immediately to the Devil, the putting them from under God's common providence, and not only expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, but conſigning them to the power and fury of that malicious miſchievous ſpirit. And accordingly is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted by all learned men; from whence we may moſt certainly conclude, what external corporal tortures and buffetings and miſeries they muſt fall into.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For were it only a pulling down the hedge of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon protection and providence that guards all men, and expoſing them to the incurſions of the devil, to be dealt with as he pleaſesh, we might eaſily preſage the miſery they would fall into.</p>
            <p>We know what the malice of the Devil againſt poor Man is, and we read enough of the effects of his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54451:18"/>cruelty and ſpight upon thoſe, he hath been let looſe upon.</p>
            <p>Malice and ſpight is the very nature of the Devil, in whom it is in the moſt extream &amp; conſummate degrees, and therefore can never be glutted with leſs than the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt miſery that Man is capable of ſuffering. And it is moſt certain, that could that curſed ſpirit have his will, men ſhould not only be miſerable in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, but in this too; and in this as well as that, to the extremity of what their natures are capable of undergoing.</p>
            <p>And we read enough to ſatisfie us of this, in thoſe unhappy and miſerable perſons that he hath had liberty of afflicting. You may read what he did to poor <hi>Job,</hi> when God put him into his hands; and you may read alſo, to what aſtoniſhing meaſures he afflicted and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the bodies of thoſe poor <hi>Daemoniacks</hi> that are mentioned in the Goſpel; now torturing them in one ſad faſhion, and then in another; now caſting them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fire, and then into the water; ſometimes bowing their bodies, and binding their head and neck even to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; ſometimes caſting them down upon the ground, and making them miſerably to tear, and gaſh, and cut themſelves; and all of them to become ſad and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpectacles unto all that looked on them.</p>
            <p>Nay, we read his malice and envy againſt Man is ſo great, that nothing belonging to him, or for his comfort, ſhould eſcape is fury. <hi>Job's</hi> Sheep and Oxen are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; and the ſtory in the Goſpel tells us, that not ſo much as a herd of Swine (might he have his will) but ſhould be drowned in the ſea, by his Legion of apoſtate malicious ſpirits.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But leſt we ſhould think it not to be for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils intereſt to torture all that were Excommunicated, and caſt out of the Church, that being one likely way
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54451:19"/>to make men more careful to keep in it, and that his intereſt in this might poſſibly over-rule his malice, and therefore to expoſe men only to his incurſions, would not prove a certainty of his tormenting them preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſecondly, we muſt know that this delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring over unto Satan, was not only expoſing, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning them over unto his power, with a command to torture and afflict them; not only like a Kings out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawing of a Rebel, but following him with a Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, in which every man that can, is commanded to ſeize and apprehend him; and conſigning him over in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of Juſtice, to be puniſhed according to the demerits of his crime.</p>
            <p>The Devil doubtleſs is ready enough to do miſchief to any perſon, whenever he can: but here in this caſe, he is not only at liberty, but under a command to do it. It is delivering to him, as to a common Lictor, whoſe very place and office it is to ſcourge and puniſh Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, and who is under obligation to inflict on them that puniſhment, that the Law hath ſentenced them unto.</p>
            <p>In this caſe the Devil is Gods Executioner; and what reſtraint ſoever his ſubtilty and ſpight againſt God might lay upon his ill nature, yet in this, he is under au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and can no more not puniſh when God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, than he can puniſh when he forbids.</p>
            <p>Thus the very phraſe in which Excommunication is expreſſed, doth ſufficiently imply, that it is not only a ſpiritual puniſhment, it being a delivering over unto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, whoſe ſpight and malice vents it ſelf againſt the bodies, as well as the Souls of men, who, might he have his will againſt man, and the utmoſt that his deviliſh malice could deſire, would leave no part of Man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched, nor any thing to be the leaſt comfort to him; but would even antedate his Hell-here, and render him
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54451:19"/>as compleatly miſerable now, as he ſhall be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>But who (to be ſure) will do this, when the Almighty lays this burthen upon him: for he is under the command of God, (as 'tis happy for us that he is) and can no more forbear doing what he commands him, than do any thing which he reſtrains him from.</p>
            <p>But this will be more clear, from what is ſaid to be the end and purpoſe of this <hi>delivering unto Satan,</hi> which in one place is ſaid to be <hi>for the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the ſpirit may be ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus;</hi> In the other, <hi>that they may learn not to blaſpheme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence it is plain, that this puniſhment was medicinal, and intended, as the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.10. <hi>to edification, and not to deſtruction;</hi> not barely a puniſhment to revenge the reproach and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry done unto Religion upon the offender, but deſigned to a merciful and good end, to effect his repentance and amendment, as all Gods puniſhments in this world are. <hi>Leſt being preſent I ſhould uſe ſharpneſs, according to the power that Chriſt hath given me, to edification, and not to deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this being clearly declared to be the end and purpoſe of this infliction, it will be eaſily apprehended that there was ſomething in it proper to effect this end; which cannot be thought to be any thing elſe, but ſome external Corporal puniſhment, which is the only thing that is of any force and efficacy with men of ſuch tempers.</p>
            <p>For I would fain know, what other thing we can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to be in this puniſhment, ſo probably and directly effective of this good end, as this.</p>
            <p>Shame and ſorrow for being caſt out of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt put from under Gods common providence and care, expoſed to the incurſions of the Devil, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54451:20"/>cut off from all hopes of future happineſs, are things very proper to bring a man to repentance, and ſuch as Excommunication may poſſibly effect in men, <hi>i. e.</hi> if they do ſeriouſly conſider and reflect upon their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But to imagine that this was all that was in this pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment towards the <hi>deſtruction of the fleſh, the ſaving of the ſpirit,</hi> and <hi>the learning not to blaſpheme,</hi> is very unreaſonable, upon many accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For firſt, theſe effects were but barely poſſible at moſt; it was poſſible ſuch a man might be aſhamed and humbled, but it was as poſſible that he might not be ſo: and to think that the Apoſtles would inflict ſo great a cenſure upon ſo great an uncertainty, or that the laſt remedy the Church had againſt obſtinate and profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Chriſtians, was only fortuitous, might poſſibly do ſome good, and as poſſibly none at all, is a conceit that many great reaſons combine together againſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And ſecondly, there is nothing in Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion directly effective of this ſorrow and ſhame, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the mediation of a ſober conſideratio, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon a mans preſent condition. It's true, did a man well weigh what a condition he was then put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, it might by the grace of God, effect ſorrow and ſhame, and great remorſe in him, which might iſſue into repentance.</p>
            <p>But ſo would the conſidering and reflection upon his obſtinate and ſcandalous life have done the ſame before, without Excommunication.</p>
            <p>Conſidering after-Excommunication could tell him no more of his dangerous condition, than it would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: for if he had any ſenſe of Religion upon him before, he could not but know, what the effects of ſin, and a vitious life, would certainly be; and if he had not that ſenſe of Religion, he would as little believe them, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard them, after Excommunication, as before it.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:54451:20"/>
            <p n="3">3. Nor thirdly, do I ſee any thing in Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and delivering to Satan, were there nothing but this in it, much more likely to awaken theſe thoughts and reflexions upon ſuch a man, than what he enjoyed, and was uſed to him before.</p>
            <p>For he did live under the miniſtration of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, where the terrors of the Lord were made known to him, and where he heard what the fate of obſtinate and flagitious ſinners was ſure to be. Nay, and farther than this, he uſually (at leaſt) did injoy the benefit of both private and publick advice, and admonition, was often told of his wickedneſs, and warned of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of it (for in that method it is certain the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church did proceed with offenders, and the Church doth imitate the ſame to this day). And if all thoſe things could not occaſion theſe thoughts, I do not ſee that there is any thing in this puniſhment (ſuppoſing it to be only Excommunicating) more likely or power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to do it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For fourthly, the perſons upon which this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was uſually inflicted, were obſtinate and notorious offenders, ſuch as had fronted and braved all former re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs and methods uſed for their amendment.</p>
            <p>Thus it more than probably was in thoſe two firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of thoſe delivered to Satan; but thus it certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was in all others afterwards. The inceſtuous <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian</hi> had avowed his ſin, and perſiſted in his inceſtuous cohabitation; for had he confeſſed the guilt, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from her whom he had inceſtuouſly taken, he would doubtleſs have been pardoned before this delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Satan, as well as he was upon theſe things abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved afterwards.</p>
            <p>And ſo (it's very likely) it was with <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> one perſiſting in his deriding the Doctrine of the Reſurrection, and future Judgment; and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54451:21"/>in the trouble that he gave to the Apoſtle in his Miniſtry, notwithſtanding milder ways of reforming both of them.</p>
            <p>And it is certain, this was the uſual method of the Church with ſuch perſons; firſt to try all fair means, exhortation, reproof, and admonition, firſt in private, and then publickly; and when theſe failed, then to fly to this as the laſt remedy.</p>
            <p>And what a little this was likely to effect upon men of ſuch daring and obſtinate tempers, (were there no more in it) may eaſily be conjectured. They that could defie and brave all the exhortations and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the Church, and its power, would eaſily do the ſame to the execution thereof; nor be much moved by being caſt out of the Communion of that, which they ſo lightly regarded the power and conſtitution of.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Nay, I adde, fifthly, that this was ſo unlikely to effect this Repentance and Salvation, that it was the moſt probable and certain way to the plain contrary.</p>
            <p>If delivering over unto Satan ſignified no more, but only caſting out of the Communion of Chriſts Church, putting from under Gods protection, and the influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his grace, and expoſing them to the Devil to be dealt with as he pleaſed;</p>
            <p>Then, inſtead of being ſaved, they ſhould more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be damned; inſtead of learning not to blaſpheme, they ſhould be put upon doing it ſo much the more. And this, inſtead of being medicinal, and to their edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, would be the more certain conſignation of them to eternal damnation.</p>
            <p>For ſure no man can think, that the Devil when he is left to his own will, will be inſtrumental to any mans Happineſs and Salvation; or that he will turn a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of Righteouſneſs, and an inſtructer in the paths of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54451:21"/>vertue and amendment, whoſe malice againſt mankind is implacable, and all whoſe ſtudy is, to betray men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vice and wickedneſs, and to render them as uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of eternal happineſs as himſelf, and to plunge them remedileſly into damnation that is prepared for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and his Angels.</p>
            <p>Might the Devil have his purpoſe upon Man, the fleſh ſhould always be rampant, and captivate the ſpirit, and both ſhould be damned in the day of the Lord Jeſus; and mens Tongues ſhould be ſet on fire by Hell, and they ſhould blaſpheme the God of Heaven, with as black and rankerous a malice, as his Apoſtate Legions.</p>
            <p>And delivering up to Satan, were this the only mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, were the direct way to put him into a power of effecting that with eaſe, which he is at ſo much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and artifice in endeavouring to accompliſh: inſtead of being an act of ſaving, it were the ſureſt way of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying men, and ſo far from being an act of kindneſs and diſcipline, it were an expreſſion of the greateſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and ſeverity in the world; it would finally defeat its own purpoſe, and put men into a deſperate condition, even before the great time of deſpair commenced, which is very rarely, or never until death.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But now in the laſt place, if we interpret the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery unto Satan in the ſenſe that I have been contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for, <hi>i. e.</hi> that it was a putting men into his power to be buffeted and afflicted with Diſeaſes and corporal puniſhments, (as <hi>Job</hi> was, as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> interprets that expreſſion) then we both ſee, that this was uſed to edification; and what a great propriety and direct effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy there is in it to produce the purpoſe it was deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto.</p>
            <p>There is nothing ſo fit for obſtinate men as a whip, nor any thing ſo likely to reclaim them, as ſmart and ſuffering: a bridle is for the mouth of the Horſe and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54451:22"/>Mule, and a rod for the back of an incorrigible fool; reproof is loſt upon a ſcorner, and ſo are all ſober and gentler methods to a man of a perverſe mind.</p>
            <p>This hath always been the way of Gods Providence, and ſtrivings with man: thoſe that make themſelves beaſts, muſt be reclaimed in a way ſutable to beaſts, which is with hardſhip and ſtripes.</p>
            <p>And as this ſeems proper, ſo it is often ſeen to be accordingly ſucceſsful. As God ſpeaks of the wild Aſs in the wilderneſs, that ſnuffs up the wind, and ſcorns to come under the diſcipline of any, <hi>yet in her month we ſhall find her, Jer.</hi> 2.24. ſo it is commonly with the moſt obſtinate men; affliction often makes them ſtoop, who ſcorned all gentler means of reformation; and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral ſmart and puniſhment, often reduces that man to ſober thinking, who hated a ſerious thought, and was as far from it as the ſole of an Aſs.</p>
            <p>We ſee this experienced every day; pains and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring pull down the proud and haughty tempers of men, correct the wild and extravagant gayeties of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, intenerate and ſoften their ſpirits, clear their eyes from the miſts that proſperity caſt before them, let them ſee the truth of things, and like the great <hi>Aſſyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> to bow to the Almighty, who a little before were apt to rival both his power and glory too.</p>
            <p>This therefore was the method that God tryed with obſtinate offenders in the Primitive times of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; &amp; therefore while the Church wanted the favor of the Civil Magiſtrate, &amp; had not power to inflict puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon men, God was pleaſed to ſupply that defect this way, and make Satan the common Lictor and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner of puniſhment upon thoſe, whom gentler methods would not reſtrain, and prevail upon.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I think are ſufficient to the purpoſe I have ſpoken them, to let men ſee, how terrible the effects
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54451:22"/>of Excommunication were in the times of the Goſpel;
<note place="margin">
                  <p>St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> calls his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom in Hom.</hi> 15. <hi>in primam ad Corinthios,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. To the deſtruction of the fleſh, <hi>i. e.</hi> as was done to holy <hi>Job.</hi> And a little after, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> That he might afflct him with ſome ſore Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, or other Diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Ambroſe, lib.</hi> 10. <hi>de poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia,</hi> inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how the Inceſtuous <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthian</hi> was delivered to Satan, anſwers thus: <hi>Sicut Domin us in animam ſancti Job non dedit poteſtatem, ſed in carnem ejus permiſit, ita &amp; hic traditur Satanae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Hierome, in cap.</hi> 5. <hi>ad Galatas: Precepit eum tradi poenitentiae in interitum &amp; vexatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem carnis, per jejunia &amp; aegrotationes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Author of the Commentary upon the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> commonly (though as ſome ſay falſely) aſcribed to St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> upon <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>ult.</hi> hath theſe words: <hi>Quali vigâ ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam ad vos?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Quali Petrus venit ad Ananiam &amp; Saphiram, &amp; Paulus ad Magum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this expreſſion, <hi>The deſtruction of the fleſh,</hi> he renders by <hi>carnis anguſtias, &amp; detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta membrorum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Pacian in Epiſt.</hi> 3. <hi>ad Sempronium,</hi> hath the ſame words.</p>
                  <p>Theodoret in locum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>Cajetanus <hi>in locum: Hinc apparet punitionem hanc fuiſſe venationem corporalem, etiam uſque ad mortem non tamen repentinam.</hi> In which perhaps he may be miſtaken, and as to the Inceſtuous perſon, certainly was; yet herein he follows St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>de Sermone Domini in Montem,</hi> ſeems to queſtion whether this did not extend unto death.</p>
                  <p>Anſwerable to theſe, you will find theſe following Learned perſons, as you have them in the large Criticks printed at <hi>London.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Vatablus <hi>in primam ad</hi> 1 Cor. 5.5. <hi>ut carne afflictus reſipiſcat. Clarius in locum terminum prefigit ſatanae, ut corpus tantum tangeret, uti in</hi> Job <hi>factum erat.</hi> Jacob. Capellus <hi>in locum,</hi> who gives an inſtance of the like puniſhment, and immediate ſeizure by Satan, out of the Life of <hi>St. Ambroſe,</hi> written by <hi>Paulinus. Grotius in locum: Nempè ut per eum morbis vexetur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To theſe may be added <hi>Aquinas in locum,</hi> if we think he can add any moment to the judgment of thoſe that we have named before him.</p>
                  <p>In the cloſe of which, I may add the Authority of our own <hi>Hammond,</hi> whoſe Judgment is, and will be valued, as long as ſound Learning flouriſheth in the world; and he in his Note E on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. contends for the reaſonableneſs of this Expoſition.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe <hi>Calvins</hi> Authority may be of credit more than they all, with ſome men, I therefore produce him in the laſt place, who both in his Expoſition upon this place, and in his Inſtitutions too, doth not deny theſe to have been the effects of Excommunication in the Apoſtles time; only contends that that was not all that was intended in this expreſſion, as he chargeth <hi>St. Chryſoſtome</hi> and others (though I do not ſee for what reaſon) to have ſaid was.</p>
               </note> and that whatever evil conſequences the Laws of our Nation have made appendant to it now, are not ſo terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as theſe were, and conſequently that there is not ſo much cauſe to cry out againſt this procedure with men, as unchriſtian, and contrary to the rules or practice of the Goſpel, and Apoſtles of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And that this notion is true, might further be proved from the teſtimony and judgment of men of great Authority and Credit in the Church of Chriſt, both Ancient and Modern, were there any need of it. Such for inſtance are St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> of old; and ſuch as <hi>Grotius, Capellus, Hamond,</hi> and almoſt all the moſt Learned men of late, who all unanimouſly contend, that this was the ſenſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering up unto Satan, and theſe the effects that uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followed Excommunication in the Primitive times, while the Church was deſtitute of the protection of the Civil Magiſtrate, and had not the power of making Laws externally to puniſh obſtinate offenders.</p>
            <p>The Learned Reader, for his fuller ſatisfaction, may at leiſure conſult the Quotations in the Margine.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:54451:23"/>
            <p>And now after theſe things, I do not well know what is wanting to our purpoſe, unleſs it be to examine ſome Objections againſt this notion of delivering to Satan, and to ſatisfie ſome ſcruples about it; to which I ſhall addreſs my ſelf, that I may leave every thing as plain as I can. And there are three or four things that will require a particular conſideration, in order to this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And firſt, it may be demanded, Why are theſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Excommunication now ceaſed? there appears nothing of this nature now, nor hath for a long time; what's the reaſon therefore, if there were ſuch things, why we ſee nothing like them now?</p>
            <p>To which Queſtion an Anſwer may be given out of what was hinted but juſt before; That theſe extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary effects laſted only till the Government of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire turned Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Till then indeed it was neceſſary that the Church ſhould have ſome ſuch power, to inforce Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and render it terrible and effective to obſtinate offenders. But when the Governours and Civil power became Chriſtian, then they might uſe the Temporal Sword, to back the Spiritual, and inforce theſe Cenſures of the Church with external puniſhments, and thereby do that, which God did by this extraordinary means.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:54451:23"/>
            <p>And therefore, as when the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, came into the plentiful land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> that Manna ceaſed by which they had been fed in a barren wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: ſo when the Church was protected by the Civil power, and the Laws of men could do that, which an extraordinary providence had done to that time, then God was pleaſed to withdraw the ſame, and leave men to their own conduct, when they were able to govern themſelves.</p>
            <p>For God was never ſo laviſh and prodigal of doing Miracles, as ſome men would make him. As he never ſuffered a Miracle to be effected, but upon ſome very great reaſon; no more did he ever interpoſe, or uſe an extraordinary power to effect that, which the power of nature, and ſecond cauſes were ſufficient for.</p>
            <p>When Kings and Emperours therefore became nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Fathers to the Church, (according to the ancient Propheſie) made Laws for the Government and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of it, and backed thoſe Laws with Sanctions of grievous puniſhments, made the intereſt of Religion their own, and guarded the peace and order of the Church with the ſame vigilancie and care, that they did their Kingdoms; then there was no ſuch great need of theſe extraordinary interpoſitions of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to this purpoſe, as was formerly, and therefore they ceaſed. Juſt as the power of Miracles, which was a long time continued in the Church, yet ceaſed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when the truth and Divinity of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was ſufficiently atteſted, and could be maintained without them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But then ſecondly, it may be demanded, Why there is ſo very little account, and ſo very few inſtances of this to be found in the Hiſtory of the Church? ſure a thing of this nature, muſt have been much taken notice of, had there been any ſuch; and it is very ſtrange that there ſhould be ſo little account of it.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:54451:24"/>
            <p>The truth of what is here objected muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, unleſs there be more examples of this thing, than I have yet either by reading, or converſing with Learned men, been able to diſcover.</p>
            <p>But yet this I think may fairly be accounted for: 1. For firſt, it is certain, and greatly lamented by Learned men, that we have but very little of the Hiſtory of thoſe early times of Chriſtianity come to us; whether it be from the iniquity of time, or of men; whether from the rage of War, or ſpight of Enemies, the artifice of Hereticks, or the induſtry of thoſe men, who can as eaſily ſuppreſs ancient Records, as falſifie and corrupt them; or from what other cauſes it hath proceeded, I know not: but the truth of the thing is too plain, and we might be aſſured of it (had our ſelves never made inquiry) by conſulting the Labours of the beſt Antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the moſt curious and unwearied ſearchers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Primitive times. Here and there ſome very great thing they have picked up, ſo as to be able to patch up a Hiſtory of ſome great mens Lives; but alas, far enough from the exactneſs and fulneſs that they deſerved: and any competent account of thoſe times would have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled them to have done.</p>
            <p>And therefore I no more wonder that we have ſo little account of this, than that we have ſo little too of many others, which it would much have advantaged us to have had.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And yet perhaps a good reaſon may be given for this, even more than for ſome other things. As for example: It may well be ſuppoſed that this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was very rare, nor was there much occaſion to make uſe of it; thoſe times were famous for Piety and zeal to Religion; thoſe good men needed not to be whipped to their duty; their own fervours, and the rage of their Enemies kept them cloſe to it; and they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54451:24"/>were ſo exerciſed with almoſt daily and continual ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings for their Religion and their Lord, that they had no leiſure or temptation to grow wanton againſt the Laws, and conſtitutions of either.</p>
            <p>And they were ſo taken up with recording their own ſufferings, and tranſmitting accounts of them (as they uſed) to other Churches, that they forget to record al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt any thing elſe: and the truth is, the giving ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the brave actions, and glorious ſufferings of their Martyrs and Confeſſors, together with ſome few Apologies for themſelves and their Religion, is almoſt all that we have left us of thoſe times.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But thirdly, it may yet further be urged, that we may point to a ſpace in the Primitive times, before the Government became Chriſtian, when ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians became very troubleſome and Schiſmatical, when this puniſhment would have been proper, and in all likelihood of moſt effect to chaſtiſe thoſe, whom all gentler methods were unſucceſsful with.</p>
            <p>And yet we do not read any thing, that this remedie, and theſe puniſhments were made uſe of. Such was the time in which that great man St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> lived, who was much harraſſed and vexed with the petulancie and faction of ſome Prieſts, and others in their carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the lapſed, (as they called thoſe that fell in times of perſecution) and in whoſe time the <hi>Novatian</hi> Schiſm broke out, which ſo troubled the Church. Now this was a proper time for this great puniſhment, and theſe effects of it would very likely have done much good.</p>
            <p>This is an Objection which ſeems to come roundly up to the matter, and doth require ſatisfaction; which I ſhall endeavour to give to it, in theſe following conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is certain, that this extream and higheſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was but very rarely uſed, or inflicted upon men;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54451:25"/>and (indeed I think I may ſay) ſcarce ever, but when the leſſer intermedial cenſures of the Church were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual and deſpiſed; ſuch were excluding men from the full Communion of the Church, and impoſing ſuch Penances upon them, as they judged the nature of their offences to require.</p>
            <p n="2">2. St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> did uſe all fair ways to direct and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form theſe erring Prieſts; yea, ſome of the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors themſelves, nay even the Martyrs, who granted Letters of Communion to many to theſe <hi>lapſi,</hi> before they had ſatisfied the Church: and threatned to uſe the cenſures of the Church againſt them, if they did not reform; and by that means did happily effect his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe on many of them; and the buſineſs of Re-bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of them, which this controverſie after grew into, was a matter of queſtion and diſpute, but not of any ill manners in the Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is plain, when all other means failed with <hi>Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and he ſtill perſiſted, or rather grew more Factious and Schiſmatical; St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> had Excommunicated him, and inflicted this higheſt cenſure upon him, had he not fled into another Country; which flight of his, ſhewed clearly what a mighty dread he had of that puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And that being the common practice of notorious and great Offenders, of all reſolvedly Factious and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks at that time, as is plain in many inſtances, and particularly of <hi>Privatus</hi> and his followers, (in St. <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> time alſo) is to me a farther clear Indication of this thing, what a mighty dread and horror they had of this puniſhment: for otherwiſe, what needed they have fled away? for the Church had no power to puniſh them in their Eſtates or Bodies any other way; and therefore had they not feared this, they might have ſtayed, and defied all the Church could do to them.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:54451:25"/>
            <p n="4">4. And fourthly, if there be any inſtance produci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of this not being uſed, and theſe effects following, when the party was deſperately fallen into ſin, and yet might be reached,</p>
            <p>It was perhaps for this only reaſon, becauſe they thought Schiſm a ſin ſo odious and provoking, and of ſuch a monſtrous guilt, that the committer of it ſcarce came within the compaſs of common charity: his caſe was hopeleſs, and his ſin ſcarce to be forgiven, or pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for; and therefore that he forfeited the charity of the Church, in uſing means for his recovery; and thoſe were never to be admitted to the Communion of the Church again, who wilfully cut off themſelves from it: they had given themſelves over to Satan in one ſenſe, and it was needleſs for the Church to do it in another.</p>
            <p>And that this is not only a conjecture, may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the great ſenſe that thoſe good Fathers (and particularly St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> himſelf) had of the guilt and evil of Schiſm, calling it almoſt the impardonable ſin, ſo extreamly ſlagitious, and its guilt ſo tranſcending, that nothing, no not Martyrdom it ſelf, was able to expiate, or atone for it.</p>
            <p>They had either no hopes that the guilt of it would be forgiven, or that the Schiſmatick could repent, and be reformed; and therefore did not uſe this laſt reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but left him off as deſperate.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But yet in the fourth place, it may be farther ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, Why was it, that afterwards this form was left off? yea, forbid to be uſed in Excommunication? for ſo learned men have obſerved, that this form of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication grew in ſome Centuries into diſuſe; yea, and tell us, that the Synod of <hi>Arles</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid this expreſſion of delivering over unto Satan, or that of <hi>Anathema Maranatha</hi> to be uſed any more in Excommunication.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:54451:26"/>
            <p>But I do not ſec any thing in this obſervation to weaken our former notion of delivering to Satan, but rather very much to confirm it; for there are two accounts that may be given of this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That now there was no need of this, nor of thoſe direful effects that were of old to inforce Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and the terror and the effect of it.</p>
            <p>As I ſaid before, the powers of the world had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Scepter of Chriſt, and the Government was become Chriſtian. Laws were made for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and peace of the Church, and backed with ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of ſharp puniſhments; which would ſupply the want of theſe buſſetings from Satan, and effect that which they were deſigned for.</p>
            <p>And therefore to do this now, and expect ſuch conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences from it, would be to tempt God to do a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle without cauſe, and to effect that by an immediate interpoſition of his providence, which ordinary means would do without it.</p>
            <p>And in the end to expoſe their ſevereſt cenſures to contempt and ſcorn, when theſe effects did not follow, which they threatned by them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They left off this in pure compaſſion and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the offender, and that they might not miniſter the leaſt occaſion of deſpair and deſpondencie unto him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Anathema Maranatha,</hi> was the ſevereſt form of their higheſt cenſures, and never uſed but againſt deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate offenders, whom they gave up as utterly hopeleſs, and never received to Communion again. And to have uſed this in Chriſtian Excommunication, would have been contradicting the very end and deſign of it, which was the Reformation and amendment of the tranſgreſſor; and ſhutting the door of the Church, and of Heaven too, for ever againſt him, who by this means they intended only the better to fit and prepare to enter in at both.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:54451:26"/>
            <p>And to have uſed the form of giving up to Satan, might (they were afraid) ſound of too much ſeverity, and perhaps render the man deſperate, and hopeleſs of ever getting out of his clutches, who had always had too much power over him, but now by this penal deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very to him, would have much more.</p>
            <p>But the firſt reaſon for this is ſufficient; and whether I be out in aſſigning this ſecond or no, it matters not.</p>
            <p>This is abundantly ſufficient (I think) to the final clearing up of what I undertook to prove, That Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication in the Apoſtles times, was not only a Spiritual puniſhment, but attended frequently with corporal external puniſhments, as ſevere, nay, more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible than any that the Laws of this Kingdom have been pleaſed to back it withal.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only add one thing farther, <hi>i. e.</hi> to give a form of Excommunication uſed after this expreſſion of delivering to Satan was left off, to let you ſee how ſharp and ſevere it was, and into what evil circumſtances he that ſuffered it was brought. It is commonly taken notice of by Learned men, and was inflicted by <hi>Syneſius</hi> upon <hi>Andronicus</hi> the Praefect of <hi>Ptolemais;</hi> and theſe are the words done into Engliſh. <hi>Let no Temple be open to</hi> Andronicus <hi>and his followers. Let every Oratory and Sanctuary be for ever ſhut againſt them. We warn all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men, and all Magiſtrates, that they ſit not at the ſame. Table, that they come not into the ſame houſe with them, and that they ſhun all company or converſe with them, as they would do infection and the Plague. And all Prieſts eſpecially we charge, that they neither ſpeak to them while they live, nor allow them rites of Chriſtian Burial when dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I think was ſevere and ſharp enough; and when men conſider that over and beſides this, the Civil Laws took notice of them, and puniſhed them, perhaps in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54451:27"/>of rayling againſt the ſeverity of the Church and Government of <hi>England</hi> in this matter, they may learn to acknowledge the great clemency and mercy of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And now I come to put a period to this diſcourſe, in ſome ſhort Reflections, and Addreſſes, eſpecially to thoſe, that want information in theſe things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That men would ſeriouſly conſider what a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous inſtance of degeneracy it is, to need Laws and correction to force them to ſuch a ſervice of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as the Holy Sacrament is.</p>
            <p>Oh, how is the true ſpirit of Chriſtianity loſt! and how different is our temper in this, from thoſe good men that have gone before us! they flocked into this ſervice, juſt as Doves to their windows, (to uſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical Scheme of ſpeaking) and needed no more court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to come to this Feaſt, than hungry men do, to ſtill their ſharp and croaking appetite.</p>
            <p>Some of them called this their <hi>daily bread;</hi> and in the Primitive times it was almoſt as frequent as their daily repaſts.</p>
            <p>Thoſe good Fathers of old were not put to the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of inviting or perſwading men to come, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them rather of the two. Men came faſt enough of their own accord, and their buſineſs was to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour they were duely qualified and fitted to come; all their work was to ſtrike an awe and reverence into them, and to heighten their ſenſe of what they went about. To which purpoſe there are ſuch high and lofty things ſaid of the myſteriouſneſs and ſacredneſs of this ſervice above any others, and ſuch great pains taken to direct men in all the methods of preparation for it, and inforcing the obſervation of thoſe methods, by ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that mighty danger and guilt of unduely coming to that Ordinance.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:54451:27"/>
            <p>Which things (by the way let me tell you) ſome guides of Souls in theſe later Ages of the Church, I think, have ſomething unreaſonably inſiſted upon, and thereby driven people into an extream on the other hand, and cauſed them to conclude it ſafer not to come at all, than to incur and hazard ſo great a danger by coming unworthily.</p>
            <p>This is a ſore evil indeed, and I dare not ſay but the imprudence (or at leaſt unſeaſonableneſs) of ſome mens inſiſting ſo much upon theſe methods of the Ancient Fathers, hath been contributive to it.</p>
            <p>The Fathers are excellent guides to us, and we may follow them; but then ought to conſider the reaſons up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the purpoſes to which they ſpake many things, and not to make uſe of their ſayings, till the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and purpoſes call upon us.</p>
            <p>Had they lived in our days, I am confident they would have ſpoken at another rate, and have been as earneſt in perſwading and convincing men of their duty, as they were in directing of it; been as ſharp upon thoſe that neglected to come ſo preparedly as they ſhould.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not this to remit any mans care in fitting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for this: God forbid! but we have a different task now upon us; and I tell you plainly, I would rather men ſhould come, though they be not ſo exactly fitted, than that they ſhould not come at all. I am ſure it is better to do our duty, though it be imperfectly, than wholly to neglect and diſregard it. I would (and by Gods aſſiſtance will) direct men as well as I can, how to come like Chriſtians and good men, duely prepared for this, but I would not <hi>beat the aire</hi> in doing this, until I had convinced men that it is really their duty to come.</p>
            <p>But to return to my purpoſe: what a ſymptome is it of a faint, and almoſt dying Religion in men, to need to be contended with, or compelled in this inſtance!</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:54451:28"/>
            <p>Thoſe good Chriſtians of old (that I have been ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of) could not be reſtrained by the ſharpeſt Laws from this ſervice, but muſt daily <hi>ante-lucano tempore</hi> (ſaid the great <hi>Pliny</hi>) riſe before day to do it, though it was made death by the Law to do ſo.</p>
            <p>Our good Fathers in the times either of Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> or the late Rebellious Uſurpers, what would not they have given for half that liberty that we enjoy! who ventured their lives, and whatever can be dear to men, rather than neglect this ſervice.</p>
            <p>Lord! what are we to theſe, who need Laws to drive us, and yet will not be driven neither? what a ſtrange unhappy peeviſh temper are we of? we neglect to go when there are no Laws to compel us, and we reſuſe to go when there are: when we are indulged and left to our liberty, then we neglect and diſregard it; and when the Laws are awakened, then we complain, and ſay we ought not to be forced, but left to our liberty. Nothing will pleaſe us, nothing ſhall work upon us; we refuſe our food, or convert it into poyſon; the means that ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us, make us worſe; and what our Governours uſe as a method to perſwade us, we uſe to a quite contrary purpoſe, and make an argument for our not being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded and prevailed with.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What peeviſh frowardneſs is this? yea, what mighty folly and weakneſs! I would we would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that in the ſecond place. We have been told that this ſervice is our neceſſary duty, and tyed upon us by asex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and plain precepts as any other ſervice in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, &amp; therefore it were folly to need any compulſion to it. But we are aſſured, it is as much our intereſt as it is our duty, and greatly conducive to all the intereſts of our Souls. What weak people are we then, that need to be beaten to our own good? and like Children, cry &amp; make a ſtir when we are dreſſed, or called to our meat.</p>
            <p>Conſider it in the caſe of the Parable, that I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54451:28"/>unto; it was a Feaſt, a Royal Entertainment that they were invited unto; nothing but kindneſs and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to them was intended; and yet we are much more our own enemies than they were; for perhaps they had meat enough of their own at home, and perhaps as good too.</p>
            <p>But alas ſo have not we; what have we of our own to feed and ſupport our ſelves upon? either nothing, or nothing comparable to what we have here, where our Souls may be feaſted, with the ſurprizing and raviſhing pleaſures of God's love, and the love of our dear Lord, and nouriſhed with the Divine Graces of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit; to which any thing that we have at home, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the entertainments of the world, or vice, are fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and dream, yea <hi>Aconite</hi> and deadly wine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Therefore inſtead of blaming our Superiours, and quarrelling with the Laws, that would compel us to come, let us ſee if we ought not rather to blame our ſelves, and reproach our own fooliſh temper, that needs all this adoe, and makes force neceſſary for us. Had we that ſenſe of our duty that we ſhould, and would we do it as became wiſe and good men, we ſhould never hear of Law, or need to fear it.</p>
            <p>But it is the neglecting, nay obſtinate reſolving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this, that makes us uneaſie, or draws any ill cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances upon us; we have none to complain of but our ſelves, nor any thing done to us, but what is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, unleſs our Governours muſt draw the guilt of our ruine upon their own heads, in neglecting to do what they can, &amp; what they ought for the avoiding of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whoſe care, I think, in the laſt place, we ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take kindly and thankfully, than ſtand quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and murmuring againſt it; inſtead of repining and complaining againſt our Governours, fall down upon our knees, and bleſs God that ſuch care is taken of us.</p>
            <p>That we are not left only to our own arbitrary will
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54451:29"/>and conduct, but that we have Fathers that conſult for us, as we do for our own Children; who give them not up only to their own wild untutored paſſions and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but conſult for them, and tye them to thoſe methods which we know good for them, though they do not think ſo themſelves.</p>
            <p>We have ſeen by too ſad an experience, how unable moſt men are to govern themſelves aright in matters of Religion; what the effects of indulging, and leaving men only to their own liberty are; and we ſhould cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſoon ſee the ſame or worſe again. Lord! what extravagancies and follies are there ſo rank and wild, that ungoverned men will not run into, when they are indulged, and left wholly to themſelves!</p>
            <p>What then do we not owe to the Divine Providence, that hath ſet us under Government both in Church and State? yea, and what acknowledgments are big enough to be made to thoſe, that conſider our temper, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult for our good, do all they can to ſave us, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain us from deſtroying our ſelves.</p>
            <p>We pray daily, that God would not leave us to our ſolves, but keep us under the influences of his Grace, and guide us by his good Spirit; and truly, I think we have need too, to pray that God will keep us in his Church, and that thoſe that watch for our Souls, may be ſtill careful and ſollicitous for us; guide us aright when we are unable to direct our ſelves, and tye us to that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that is ſo neceſſary and good for us, when we grow wanton and regardleſs of it.</p>
            <p>That when the great day of the Lord Jeſus commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, they may give up their accounts with joy, and bleſs God for the ſucceſs of their labor and care; and we alſo may riſe up, and bleſs God for them, and bleſs him with them, and all of us be eternally happy in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of him, <hi>to whom be praiſe and honour and glory, now and for evermore. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:54451:29"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>Fincham Gardi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. APerſwaſive to Communion with the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Reſolution of ſome Caſes of Conſcience which reſpect Church-Communion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Caſe of Indifferent things uſed in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, propoſed and Stated, by conſidering theſe Queſtions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. A Diſcourſe about Edification.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Reſolution of this Caſe of Conſcience, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church of</hi> Englands <hi>Symbolizing ſo far as it doth with the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>makes it unlawful to hold Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church of</hi> England?</p>
            <p n="6">6. A Letter to <hi>Anonymus,</hi> in anſwer to his three Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> about Church-Communion.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Certain Caſes of Conſcience reſolved, concerning the Lawfulneſs of joyning with Forms of Prayer in Publick Worſhip. In two Parts.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Caſe of mixt Communion: Whether it be Lawful to Separate from a Church upon the account of promiſcuous Congregations and mixt Communions?</p>
            <p n="9">9. An Anſwer to the Diſſenters Objections againſt the Common Prayers, and ſome other parts of Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice preſcribed in the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. The Caſe of Kneeling at the Holy Sacrament ſtated and reſolved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In two Parts.</p>
            <p n="11">11. A Diſcourſe of Profiting by Sermons, and of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to hear where men think they can profit moſt.</p>
            <p n="12">12. A ſerious Exhortation, with ſome important Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, relating to the late Caſes about Conformity, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to the preſent Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. An Argument to Union; taken from the true Intereſt of thoſe Diſſenters in <hi>England</hi> who profeſs and call themſelves Proteſtants.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:54451:30"/>
            <p n="14">14. Some Conſiderations about the Caſe of Scandal, or giving Offence to Weak Brethren.</p>
            <p n="15">15. The Caſe of Infant-Baptiſm, in Five Queſtions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. A Diſcourſe concerning Conſcience; wherein an Account is given of the <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. The Charge of Scandal, and giving Offence by Conformity, Refelled, and Reflected back upon Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. A Diſcourſe about the charge of Novelty upon the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> made by the Papiſts asking of us the Queſtion, Where was our Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Luther?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Diſcourſe about Tradition, ſhewing what is meant by it, and what Tradition is to be received and what Tradition is to be rejected.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The difference of the Caſe between the Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Proteſtants from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Proteſtant Reſolution of Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. A Diſcourſe concerning a Guide in matters of Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Companion to the Temple: or, a help to Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the uſe of the Common prayer, divided into Four parts. 1. Of Morning and Evening Prayer. 2. Of the Litany, with the Occaſional Prayers and Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings. 3. Of the Communion Office, with the Offices of Baptiſm, Catechiſm, and Confirmation. 4. Of the Occaſional Offices, <hi>viz</hi> Matrimony, Viſitation of the Sick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The whole being carefully Corrected, and how put into one Volume. By <hi>Thomas Comber,</hi> D. D. Sold by <hi>Abel Swalle</hi> at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn,</hi> at the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
